{
  "title": "Data_Structure - Array — Slot 1 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Array — Slot 1",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>An array \\(A \\) of length \\(n \\) with distinct elements is said to be bitonic if there is an index \\(1 \\leq i \\leq n \\) such that \\(A[1..i] \\) is sorted in the non-decreasing order and \\(A[i+1..n] \\) is sorted in the non-increasing order.  <br>\nWhich ONE of the following represents the best possible asymptotic bound for the worst-case number of comparisons by an algorithm that searches for an element in a bitonic array \\(A \\)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta(n) \\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta(1) \\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta(\\log ^2 n) \\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta(\\log n) \\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta(\\log n) \\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460804/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-31#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Let \\( A \\) be an array containing integer values. The distance of \\( A \\) is defined as the minimum number of elements in \\( A \\) that must be replaced with another integer so that the resulting array is sorted in non-decreasing order. The distance of the array \\( [2,5,3,1,4,2,6] \\) is _____ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "3",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422872/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-25#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>What is the worst-case number of arithmetic operations performed by recursive binary search on a sorted array of size n? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (\\sqrt{n})\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta ( \\log _2 (n))\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta ( n^2)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta ( n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta ( \\log _2 (n))\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357532/gate-cse-2021-set-2-question-8#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Let P be an array containing n integers. Let t be the lowest upper bound on the number of comparisons of the array elements, required to find the minimum and maximum values in an arbitrary array of n elements. Which one of the following choices is correct? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(t \\gt 2n-2\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(t \\gt 3\\lceil \\frac{n}{2}\\rceil \\text{ and } t\\leq 2n-2\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(t \\gt n \\text{ and } t\\leq 3\\lceil \\frac{n}{2}\\rceil\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(t \\gt \\lceil \\log_2(n)\\rceil \\text{ and } t\\leq n\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(t \\gt n \\text{ and } t\\leq 3\\lceil \\frac{n}{2}\\rceil\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357450/gate-cse-2021-set-1-question-2#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>If an array A contains the items 10, 4, 7, 23, 67, 12 and 5 in that order, what will be the resultant array A after third pass of insertion sort? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>67,12,10,5,4,7,23</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>4,7,10,23,67,12,5</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>4,5,7,67,10,12,23</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>10,7,4,67,23,12,5</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>4,7,10,23,67,12,5</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/331354/isro2020-33\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Consider a 2-dimensional array x with 10 rows and 4 columns, with each element storing a value equivalent to the product of row number and column number. The array is stored in row-major format. If the first element x[0][0] occupies the memory location with address 1000 and each element occupies only one memory location, which all locations (in decimal) will be holding a value of 10? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(1018,1019\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(1022,1041\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(1017,1036\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(1000,1399\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(1017,1036\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "Originally all Options are wrong. We have modified one option.<br><a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/331475/isro2020-18\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>An array A consists of n integers in locations A[0],A[1],...A[n-1]. It is required to shift the elements of the array cyclically to the left by k places, where \\(1 \\leq k \\leq (n-1)\\). An incomplete algorithm for doing this in linear time, without using another array is given bellow. Complete the algorithm by filling in the blanks.<br><pre><code> min=n; i=0;\nwhile(_________) {\n    temp= A[i]; j=i;\n    while(_________) {\n        A[j]= _______;\n        j=(j+k) mod n;\n        if(j &lt; min) then\n        min = j;\n    }\n    A[(n+i-k) mod n]=_______;\n    i=________;\n    \n}</code></pre> <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(i  \\gt \\min ; \\quad j !=(n+1) \\bmod n ; \\quad A[j+k] \\quad \\text { temp; } \\quad i+1 ;\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(i \\lt \\min ; \\quad j !=(n+i) \\bmod n ; \\quad A[j+k] \\quad \\text { temp; } \\quad i+1 ;\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(i \\gt \\min ; \\quad j !=(n+i+k) \\bmod n ; \\quad A[j+k] \\quad \\text { temp; } \\quad i+1 ;\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(i \\lt \\min ; \\quad j !=(n+i-k) \\bmod n ; \\quad A[(j+k) \\bmod n] \\quad \\text { temp; } \\quad i+1 ;\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(i \\lt \\min ; \\quad j !=(n+i-k) \\bmod n ; \\quad A[(j+k) \\bmod n] \\quad \\text { temp; } \\quad i+1 ;\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/213576/isro2018-12\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Let A be an array of 31 numbers consisting of sequence of 0's followed by a sequence of 1's.\nThe problem is to find the smallest index i that A[i] is 1 by probing the minimum numbers of\nlocations in A. The worst case number of probes performed by an optimal algorithm is\n_____________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "5",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118331/gate2017-1-48#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>The average number of key comparisons required for a successful search for sequential search on n items is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2016)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{n}{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{n-1}{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{n+1}{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{n+1}{2}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2742/gate1996-2-13-isro2016-28\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following two C code segments. Y and X are one and two dimensional arrays of size n and nxn respectively, where \\(2\\leq n\\leq 10\\). Assume that in both code segments, elements of Y are initialized to 0 and each element X[i][j] of array X is initialized to i+j. Further assume that when stored in main memory all elements of X are in same main memory page frame.   <br> Code segment 1:<pre><code>//initialize elements of Y to 0\n//initialize elements X[i][j] of X to i+j\nfor(i = 0; i &lt; n; i++)\nY[i] += X[0][i]; </code></pre>  Code Segment 2:<pre><code>//initialize elements of Y to 0\n//initialize elements X[i][j] of X to i+j\nfor(i = 0; i &lt; n; i++)\nY[i] += X[i][0];</code></pre> Which of the following statements is/are correct?  <br>S1: Final contents of array Y will be same in both code segments <br> S2: Elements of array X accessed inside the for loop shown in code segment 1 are contiguous in main memory <br> S3: Elements of array X accessed inside the for loop shown in code segment 2 are contiguous in main memory <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Only S2 is correct</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Only S3 is correct</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Only S1 and S2 are correct</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Only S1 and S3 are correct</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Only S1 and S2 are correct</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8486/gate2015-3-40#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>A frame buffer array is addressed in row major order for a monitor with pixel locations starting from (0,0) and ending with (100,100). What is address of the pixel(6,10)? Assume one bit storage per pixel and starting pixel location is at 0. <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2014)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1016</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1006</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>610</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>616</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>1016</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/53819/isro2014-48\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Suppose there are 11 items in sorted order in an array. How many searches are required on the average, if binary search is employed and all searches are successful in finding the item? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2014)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(3.00\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>3.46</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2.81</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>3.33</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(3.00\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/16124/isro2014-28\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>In an array of 2N elements that is both 2-ordered and 3-ordered, what is the maximum number of positions that an element can be from its position if the array were 1-ordered? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>N/2</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>2N-1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/43767/isro-2013-9\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Let A(1:8, -5:5, -10:5) be a three dimensional array. How many elements are there in the array A? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1200</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1408</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>33</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1050</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>1408</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/43751/isro-2013-1\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>A one dimensional array A has indices 1....75. Each element is a string and takes up three memory words. The array is stored at location 1120 decimal. The starting address of A[49] is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1267</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1164</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1264</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1169</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>1264</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/48050/isro2009-29\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}